RG 069:100, Mathias Spiess Papers
Connecticut State Library
Mathias Spiess papers
1892-1944
Connecticut State Library
Spiess, Mathias
1.25 cubic feet
The papers consist of material pertaining to Mathias Spiess who was an amateur historian with an interest in Connecticut Indians and the town of Manchester. Spiess in 1936 served as a Republican selectman and in 1937 and 1938 was a police commissioner for the town of Manchester. Included in the papers are correspondence, subject files, writings, and maps.
RG069_100
T001618
Biographical Note
Mathias Spiess was born in Brooklyn, New York, in 1873, the son of William and Mary Spiess. He first came to Manchester in 1896, settling there permanently in 1903 after his marriage to Fredericka Haas Spiess.
After retiring as a tobacco broker, Spiess devoted his energies to his activities as an historian. In 1924 he co-authored a history of the town of Manchester. He was also known as a writer of the history of Indian tribes in Connecticut. He authored many publications on Indians, including a monograph published by the Connecticut Tercentenary Commission.
Spiess also devoted his energies to civic activities as well. After World War I he aided the fund drive for the erection of the Manchester Memorial Hospital. In 1936 he served as a Republican selectman, and in 1937 and 1938 he was a police commissioner for the town of Manchester. During World War II he headed the Manchester War Records Committee.
Spiess died on December 19, 1959, at the age of 86, three years after the death of his wife.
Scope and Content
The papers were arranged into five series. The series include Correspondence, Subject Files, Writings, Maps and Restricted.
Series 1. Correspondence, 1903-1944, include correspondence to and from Mathias Spiess on matters dealing with archaeology, Native American history, local history, and politics.
Series 2. Subject Files, 1924-1943, consists of various subjects such as Indian affairs, Connecticut Tercentennary, genealogy, and legal documents. Miscellaneous folder consists of illegible postcards and Manchester Board of Police Commissioners Stationary.
Series 3. Writings, 1933-1936, include the speeches and writings of Mathias Spiess. Topics include "What an Agnostic Believes" and the beliefs of Connecticut Indians.
Series 4. Maps, 1892-1935, consists of seven maps all of Conneticut. Two maps are hand drawn and show Mt. Tom and East Haddam. Another gives the location of indian trails.
Series 5. Restricted, 1928
Arrangement
Series 1. Correspondence, 1903-1944
Series 2. Subject Files, 1924-1943
Series 3. Writings, 1933-1936, undated
Series 4. Maps, 1892-1935, undated
Series 5. Restricted, 1928
Related Material
None.
Bibliography
Books
National Society of the Colonial Dames of America in the State of Connecticut. Connecticut circa 1625, its Indian trails, villages and sachendoms, published by the Connecticut society of the colonial dames of America, inc., from data collected by Mathias Spiess; edited by Elinor H. Bulkeley Ingersoll. Wethersfield, CT, 1934.
Spiess, Mathias and Percy W. Bidwell. History of Manchester, Connecticut. South Manchester, CT: Centennial Committee of the Town of Manchester, 1924.
Pamphlets
Spiess, Mathias. The Indians of Connecticut. New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1933.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Connecticut--History; Connecticut Tercentenary Commission (1935); Indians of North America--Connecticut; Manchester (Conn.)--History
Places:
Manchester (Conn.); Hartford (Conn.)
Persons:
Spiess, Mathias, 1873-1959; Carver, George Washington, 1864?-1943
Document Types:
Clippings; Correspondence; Legal Documents; Maps; Publications; Reports
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Provenance
The Mathias Spiess Papers were donated by Mr. Everett Fish to the State Library in June 1982.
Container List
- Series 1. Correspondence, 1903-1944
  - Archeological, 1935-1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ayers, Harral, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B, 1923-1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C, 1903-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cadwell, Harold, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carver, George Washington, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cheney, 1930-1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cheney, Horace, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Connecticut Historical Society, 1920-1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Connecticut State Library, 1920-1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Connecticut Tercentenary Commission, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - D, 1933-1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - E-F, 1928-1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - G-H, 1920-1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hale, C. Wesley, 1933-1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - J, 1920-1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - K, 1932-1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - L, 1913-1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - M, 1915-1944 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Manchester Chamber of Commerce, 1930-1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Manchester Evening Herald, 1917-1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Manchester Selectmen, 1914-1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Markus, Emil, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mills, Lewis S., 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - N-O, 1916-1938 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - P, 1930-1943 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - R, 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - S, 1931-1940 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Silver Star, Sachem (Grand Chief), 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Spiess, 1917-1942 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - T, 1931-1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Tantaquidgeon, Gladys (Mohegan Tribe), 1921-1931 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - U-W, 1924-1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Whiton Memorial Library, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Y, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Series 2. Subject Files, 1924-1943
  - American Indian Federation, 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Connecticut Tercentenary, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1933-1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Drawings/Pictures, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Geneology, 1930-1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Some documents are in German
  - Indian history, 1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Legal documents, 1924-1931 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Manchester Centennial, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Solicitations, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series 3. Writings, 1933-1936, undated
  - Writings, 1933-1936, undated (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
- Series 4. Maps, 1892-1935, undated
  - Map of Western Connecticut, 1932; 1 map; State of Connecticut. (Box Oversized Map Case)
  - Map of East Hartford/Manchester, undated; 1 map
  - Hand Drawn Map of Mt. Tom, undated; 1 map; 1 inch = 400 feet
  - Hand Drawn Map of Mt. Tom/East Haddam, undated; 1 map
  - Map of the Town of Manchester, 1892; 1 map; Prepared by H.R. Fitch for Bowers' Manchester Directory.
  - State of Connecticut, State Geological and Natural History Survey, W.E. Britton, Superintendent, Map Showing the Glacial Geography of Connecticut, 1930; 1 map; Prepared by Richard Foster Flint.
  - Map of Indian Trails with cover letter, 1935; 1 map
- Restricted, 1928
  - Correspondence
    - Restricted, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 1)